Finding Aid for Susan Wineberg papers, 1965-2009
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Susan Wineberg papers 1965-2009, 1977-2003
Wineberg, Susan.
1 oversize folders
68 linear feet (in 69 boxes)
89449 Aa 2
Susan Wineberg is a historian of Ann Arbor, Mich., and historic preservationist. She became involved in historic preservation in 1974 and has served as a commissioner on the Ann Arbor Historic District Commission (1982, 1984-1988) and as a member on its committees since 1977. Wineberg also has authored books and articles on historic buildings in Ann Arbor and been active in other local organizations. The collection includes correspondence, articles, brochures, clippings, printed ephemera and realia, photographs, and subject files relating mostly to Ann Arbor, Detroit, and Michigan historic properties and businesses.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was received in several accessions from Susan Cee Wineberg (Donor no. 5400 ) beginning in 1974.
Periodic additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Susan Cee Wineberg is an Ann Arbor historian and historic preservationist. She was born on February 5, 1946 in Chicago, Illinois, but moved to Ann Arbor in 1964. She received her B.A. (1967) and M.A. (1971) in Near Eastern Studies and an M.A. (1976) in Anthropology from the University of Michigan. In 1984, she became a Ph.D. candidate specializing in archaeology. She also married Lars Bjorn in 1984. While a student at the University of Michigan, she became interested in local history and historic preservation through her research on her home at 311 E. Ann Street and her involvement on the Save the Waterman-Barbour Gym Committee in 1974. Beginning in 1977, she became involved with the Ann Arbor Historic District Commission and other local history and preservation groups. From 1980 to 1984, she was assistant to the photography curator at the Bentley Historical Library. She also has conducted freelance research on many historic buildings in the Washtenaw County area. She received state grants in 1982 to document central Ann Arbor architecture before 1940 and in 1989 to document a proposed Downtown Historic Marker Project. In addition, she has published articles about historic buildings in the Ann Arbor Observer and other publications, and co-authored Historic Buildings, Ann Arbor, Michigan in 1992 with Marjorie Reade. In 1994, she received an M.S. in Historic Preservation from Eastern Michigan University. As an activist and researcher, Wineberg has collected the records of committees and organizations in which she has participated and other materials about Ann Arbor's architectural history.
Wineberg was a member of the Ann Arbor Historic District Commission from April to October 1982, November 1984 to June 1985, September 1985 to September 1988, and 2002 to 2008. The Historic District Commission was established by city ordinance in 1971 as the successor to the Historical Commission. The Ann Arbor mayor appoints seven members to the commission, who are then approved by the City Council. The commission's functions include: to identify historically and architecturally significant properties, landmarks, and areas; to oversee the city's historic districts and investigate the adoption of new historic districts or properties; to develop design guidelines and review applications for the construction, alteration, or removal of properties within historic districts; and to provide information about local history and encourage appreciation of local heritage. Each month the Historic District Commission hears petitions from owners of protected property who are seeking to alter or renovate their buildings. The commission reviews and monitors the projects to ensure they follow an approved plan.
Wineberg also has chaired and served on multiple committees related to the commission's activities between 1977 and the present. Between 1977 and 1983, Wineberg served on the Division Street Historic District Study Committee (also known as the Old Fourth Ward Historic District Study Committee after 1981). The Ann Arbor City Council appointed the committee in 1977 as a result of petitions to designate neighborhood structures as historic landmarks. The committee was composed of nine Historic District Commission members and ten interested residents of the area. In 1978, the committee proposed the Ann Street Historic Block. Between 1980 and 1983, it proposed that the remaining area under study be designated the Old Fourth Ward Historic District. Wineberg researched all of the buildings that became protected under the ordinances.
Between 1986 and 1988, Wineberg was chair of the Landmarks Historic Preservation Study Committee. The Ann Arbor City Council appointed this committee in 1986 to identify, research, and recommend landmarks for preservation under a local ordinance. It consisted of current members of the Ann Arbor Historic District Commission and six Ann Arbor citizens. The committee recommended forty-seven properties for protection. They also determined that a register of all historically significant resources in the city was necessary to protect properties within historic districts as well as those individual historic properties outside of historic districts. The committee drafted an ordinance with new incentives and a mission statement. It passed unanimously in April 1988 and resulted in the Ann Arbor Register of Historic Places.
Wineberg was a member of the Downtown Historic District Study Committee between 1986 and 1992. The Ann Arbor City Council created the study committee in 1979 to study how to best preserve the historic character of downtown. It was composed of Historic District commissioners, downtown owners, and residents. In 1988, the committee recommended the passage of three historic commercial districts and two historic residential districts: Main Street, State Street, Kerrytown, East William Street, and East Liberty Block. By 1989, after much debate, only the Main Street, Kerrytown, and East William Street Historic Districts were approved. The other two were approved in 1992.
Wineberg has served as a member of the Awards Committee of the Ann Arbor Historic District Commission from 1988 to the present and as its chair from 1990 to 1998. The Awards Committee recognizes building owners and organizations for their efforts to preserve the city's architectural heritage.
Despite success in developing historic districts and registering properties with the Register of Historic Places, much of this work was invalidated in 2001, when the Michigan Court of Appeals declared Ann Arbor’s Individual Historic Properties register (IHP) invalid. This ruling was the result of a lawsuit by the Draprop Corporation, which tried to claim that the city did not have the right to designate a property to be historic without the owner’s consent. While the court did not agree with Draprop, they did agree that Ann Arbor’s historic districts did not meet the definition of a historic district as defined by Michigan law.
Wineberg was appointed to the Individual Historic Properties Historic District Study Committee in 1990 and has served as chair since 1993. The Ann Arbor City Council created the standing committee in 1990 to research and recommend individual properties that meet the criteria of the Historic District Code. The committee consists of nine appointed members who reside or own property in Ann Arbor, at least two of whom are from the Ann Arbor Historic District Commission and one of whom is an architectural historian. In 1994, the committee succeeded in adding seventy-three properties to the Ann Arbor Register of Historic Places.
In 1989, Wineberg served as a research consultant for the Downtown Historical Street Exhibit Program. The program was sponsored by the Ann Arbor Historic District Commission and the Citizen's Council of the Downtown Development Authority as a means to showcase local history. The exhibit program consisted of published guides and permanent outdoor displays focusing on urban development.
Wineberg has been active in other local organizations separate from the Historic District Commission. She was a founding member and secretary of the Old Fourth Ward Association from 1984 to the present. The Old Fourth Ward Association is a non-profit corporation that strives to maintain and improve the quality of life, historic architecture, and residential character of the Old Fourth Ward Historic District. It also fosters the development of social relationships and community identity in the neighborhood. In addition, Wineberg has been a board member of the Ann Arbor Historical Foundation since 1986, a member of the Lower Town Historic District Study Committee (2005-2006), and a member of the Germantown (4th and 5th Avenue) Historic District Study Committee (2009-2010). She also has been involved in the Washtenaw County Historical Society since 1988, including vice-president (1993-1994), president (1995-1999), chair of the Museum Planning Committee, and was editor of The Impression for five years (1999-2003).
The Susan Wineberg Papers document local efforts to research and protect historic properties in the Ann Arbor area. The collection is a rich source of information for the history of many buildings and areas in Ann Arbor. Wineberg has assembled clippings, stories, records, and photocopies of pictures about local preservation, conflicts over preservation laws, and historic buildings. The collection documents not only Wineberg's involvement in historic preservation, but also the activities of governmental and community organizations that have sought to preserve Ann Arbor's heritage and encourage adoption of their sense of responsible development. Moreover, the records reveal the evolution of historic preservation since the 1970s. They document the debates within the community between those who favor governmental measures that aim to protect the city's historic properties and those who view such protective ordinances and regulations as an intrusion on individual property rights. Additionally, several of the series document the history of Ann Arbor, Detroit, Washtenaw County, and Michigan through collected photocopies, photographs, and assorted ephemera.
The collection is organized into nine series: Personal Files, Ann Arbor Historic District Commission, Ann Arbor Historic Preservation and Development Materials, Audio Materials, Visual Materials, Research / Reference files, Printed Ephemera and Realia, Printed Ephemera and Realia, 1969-2004, Collected Historical Materials, and Washtenaw County Historical Society.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor Historic District Commission (Mich.); Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Buildings, structures, etc.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--History.; Architecture--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Conservation and restoration.; Downtown Historic District (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Historic buildings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Historic buildings--Michigan--Detroit.; Historic districts--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Historic preservation--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Historical markers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Jews--Michigan.; Old Fourth Ward Association (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Old Fourth Ward Historic District (Ann Arbor, Mich.); University of Michigan--Buildings.; Urban renewal--Citizen participation--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Washtenaw County Historical Society.; Wineberg, Susan.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Street (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Historic buildings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Historic buildings--Michigan--Detroit.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Buildings, structures, etc.; Detroit (Mich.)--Buildings, structures, etc.; Ann Arbor Historic District Commission (Mich.)
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Videotapes.; Slides (photographs)
- Personal Files
  The Personal Files series, organized alphabetically, includes biographical information, such as curriculum vitae, personal correspondence, and some of Wineberg's writings relating to historic properties in Ann Arbor, Michigan.
  - Biographical Information (Box 1)
  - Clippings 1969-1998 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1974-2007 (Box 1)
  - Wedding Photographs, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Writings
    - "The Allmendinger Piano and Organ Company," 1991 (Box 1)
    - "Ann Arbor's Catalogue Houses," 1993 (Box 1)
    - "Ann Arbor's Earliest Buildings: 1824-1837" 1989 (Box 1)
    - "The Guy Beckley House," 1988 (Box 1)
    - "The Herman Miller Residence, 839 W. Huron Ave, Ann Arbor, Michigan," 1986 (Box 1)
    - "History of Residence at 311 (325 and 339) E. Ann Street, Ann Arbor, Michigan" (Box 1)
    - "History of the Bethel A.M.E. Church, Ann Arbor, Michigan," 1996 (Box 1)
    - "Huron Street in Ann Arbor, Michigan: The Transformation of a Residential Street," 1992 (Box 1)
    - "The Little White House at 1015 Wall Street, Ann Arbor, Michigan," 1989 (Box 1)
      The house was moved to 500 N. Main in June 1990
    - "Lost Ann Arbor: The Town That Once Was," 1994 (Box 1)
      Susan Wineberg's master's thesis for the Historic Preservation Program at Eastern Michigan University
    - "The Luick Mill at Kerrytown," 1989 (Box 1)
    - "The Michigan Furniture Company and the Changing Furniture Industry in Ann Arbor, Michigan," 1990 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous 1973-1994 (Box 1)
    - "More History from Wall St: Braced Frame Construction in the 1830s" 1998 (Box 1)
    - "North Main Revitalization," 1993 (Box 1)
    - "One Man's Meat Is Another Man's Poison: The State Theater and the Michigan Central Railroad Depot," 1992 (Box 1)
    - "Preliminary Report for Nomination to the National Register of Historic Places," 1989 (Box 1)
    - "Promoting the Old Fourth Ward District, Ann Arbor, Michigan," 1992 (Box 1)
    - "Remodeling Your Home: An Enduring American Tradition," 1989 (Box 1)
      includes information on the Old Fourth Ward
    - "The Sofa-Bed: An Enduring Furniture from over 150 Years," 1992 (Box 1)
    - "2961 Dexter Avenue" 1982 (Box 1)
- Ann Arbor Historic District Commission
  The Ann Arbor Historic District Commission series includes materials from multiple organizations and committees involved in historic preservation or planned development in Ann Arbor, which Wineberg collected as a member of the commission. It also includes materials Wineberg assembled as a researcher on these topics. The largest part of the series documents the Ann Arbor Historic District Commission and its various committees for the years 1974-1997. The meeting minutes of the commission are important for their documentation of the review process used for the renovation and alteration of protected properties.
  The records of the following committees of the commission are included in this series: Awards Committee, Division Street Historic District Study Committee, Downtown Historic District Study Committee, Downtown Historical Street Exhibit Program, Individual Historic Properties Historic District Study Committee, and Landmarks Historic District Study Committee.
  - General, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Agenda Packets and Meeting Minutes
    - 1982-1994, 14 folders (Box 1)
    - 1995-1997, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Ann Arbor Register of Historic Places 1988, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Annual Reports 1981-1983 (Box 2)
  - Awards Committee
    The records of the Awards Committee are organized chronologically and contain minutes, memoranda, correspondence, lists of selected properties under consideration, and clippings.
    - 1974, 1978, 1984-2007, 9 folders (Box 2)
    - 2008 (Box 3)
  - Background Information about Commissioners 1987 (Box 3)
  - Centennial Business Awards 1986-2007 (Box 3)
  - Division Street Historic District Study Committee (also known as the Old Fourth Ward Historic District Study Committee)
    The records of the Division Street Historic District Study Committee are organized by topic and contain reports, correspondence, meeting notes, research on selected individual properties, and drafts relating to the ordinances.
    - General 1977-1982, undated (Box 3)
    - Ann Street Historic Block Ordinance 1977-1979, 1982 undated (Box 3)
    - Old Fourth Ward Historic District Ordinance 1981-1984, undated (Box 3)
    - Preliminary Report," Old Fourth Ward Historic District, Ann Arbor, Michigan," circa 1980 (Box 3)
  - Downtown Historic District Study Committee
    Materials from the Downtown Historic District Study Committee include reports, design guidelines, meeting notes, and memoranda.
    - General 1988-1992 (Box 3)
    - Meeting Minutes and Memoranda 1985-1992, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Reports and Guidelines 1989-1990 (Box 3)
  - Downtown Historical Street Exhibit Program 1987-1997, 3 folders (Box 3)
    Folders for the Downtown Historical Street Exhibit Program contain grant proposals, mission statements, reports, correspondence, and guidebooks for the Downtown Street and Courthouse Square exhibits.
  - Easements (Box 3)
  - Individual Historic Properties Historic District Study Committee
    For the Individual Historic Properties Historic District Study Committee, the materials are organized chronologically and include lists of researched properties, meeting notes, and clippings.
    - 1986-2001, 20 folders (Box 3)
    - 2002-2005, 4 folders (Box 14)
  - Kerrytown Pedestrian Improvements 1984-1990 (Box 14)
  - Landmarks Historic District Study Committee
    The records of the Landmarks Historic District Study Committee are organized by genre and include reports, correspondence with owners, meeting notes, preparation for hearings and the proposed ordinance, and clippings.
    - General Information, Documentation, and Reports 1986-1988 (Box 14)
    - Correspondence with Owners 1987-1988 (Box 14)
    - Memoranda 1986-1988 (Box 14)
    - Minutes 1986-1988 (Box 14)
    - Ordinance and Hearings 1987-1988 (Box 14)
    - Publications, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Staff Director Position 1982-1988 (Box 14)
  - Ordinances (Box 14)
  - Street Exhibit Program
    - 1987-2002, 8 folders (Box 14)
    - 2002-2008, 4 folders (Box 15)
  - Lower Town
    - General, 4 folders (Box 15)
    - Ordinance Discussion (Box 15)
    - Public Hearings (Box 15)
    - Study Committee (Box 15)
  - Northside (Box 15)
  - Chronological Files
    - 1990 (Box 16)
    - 1998 (Box 16)
    - 1999 (Box 16)
    - 2001 (Box 16)
    - 2002, 12 folders (Box 16)
    - 2003, 9 folders (Box 16)
    - 2004, 12 folders (Box 16)
    - 2005, 13 folders (Box 16)
    - 2006, 11 folders (Box 16)
    - 2007, 3 folders (Box 16)
    - 2007, 8 folders (Box 17)
    - 2008, 3 folders (Box 17)
  - Website 2006 (Box 17)
  - Bylaws (Box 17)
  - Tax Credits (Box 17)
  - New Construction (Box 17)
  - Trees in Historic Districts (Box 17)
  - Window Brochure and Policies (Box 17)
  - Policies and Concerns 2003 (Box 17)
  - Procedures and Ordinances (Box 17)
  - Retreat 2004, 2006-2007, 3 folders (Box 17)
  - Guidelines 2008 (Box 17)
  - Staff and Numbers (Box 17)
  - Coordinator 2005-2006, 2 folders (Box 17)
  - Bylaws 2007 (Box 17)
  - Monitor List (Box 17)
  - Ordinance Revision (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 17)
  - Preservation Week 1977 (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 18)
  - Ordinance Revision 2006 (Box 18)
  - Washtenaw County (Box 18)
- Ann Arbor Historic Preservation and Development Materials
  The Ann Arbor Historic Preservation and Development Materials series includes general reports from other local organizations concerned with planning and historic preservation. These include the Downtown Plan Steering Committee and the Old Fourth Ward Association. Also in this series are Wineberg's files of clippings and other information about local issues, such as improvements made on Liberty Street, development in the downtown area, and easements for historical preservation.
  - Ann Arbor Area Preservation Alliance 1987-1991 (Box 18)
  - Downtown Plan Steering Committee
    - Ann Arbor Downtown Plan 1988, 2 folders (Box 18)
    - Ann Arbor Downtown Walking Tour (Box 18)
  - Old Fourth Ward Association
    - Announcements 1985-1997 (Box 18)
    - By-laws (Box 18)
    - Correspondence 1980-1997 (Box 18)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 18)
    - Newsletters 1985-1996 (scattered) (Box 18)
    - General (Box 18)
    - Chronological 2001-2006, 4 folders (Box 18)
    - General (Box 19)
    - 1998 (Box 19)
  - Subject Files
    - Ann Arbor Downtown Development
      - 1965-1997, 3 folders (Box 19)
      - General, 2 folders (Box 19)
      - 2005-2006, 2 folders (Box 19)
    - Ann Arbor Historic District Commission (Box 19)
    - Buildings (Box 19)
    - Central Area Plan 1971-1973, 1991-1993 (Box 19)
    - Downtown Development Authority 1982-1998 (Box 19)
    - Easements (Box 19)
    - Economic Development Corp. 1980-1988 (Box 19)
    - Liberty Street Improvements 1984-1987 (Box 19)
    - Library Lot 1988-1991 (Box 19)
    - Loft Space development 1987-1994 (Box 19)
    - Midtown Group 1989 (Box 19)
    - Old Fourth Ward 1955-1994 (Box 19)
    - Ann Arbor Historical Foundation, 2 folders (Box 19)
    - Huron, Division, 5th 2004 (Box 19)
    - Conservation Districts (Box 19)
    - Pioneer Society 1994, 1997, 2 folders (Box 19)
    - Braced Frame Paper 1997 (Box 19)
    - Historic Buildings Book 1992, 1998 (Box 19)
    - Old Fourth Ward Research (Box 20)
    - Old Fourth Ward Association (Box 20)
    - Ann Arbor Preservation Alliance (Box 20)
    - Ann Arbor Historic Preservation (Box 20)
    - Markers/Plaques (Box 20)
    - "Ammunition" (Box 20)
    - Downtown Development Authority (Box 20)
    - Revolving Funding (Box 20)
    - Ann Arbor Historic Foundation Kempf House (Box 20)
    - Historic Buildings (Box 20)
    - Lists (Box 20)
    - Loft Conversions (Box 20)
    - Old West Side Ordinance Revision 1990 (Box 20)
    - Northside Study 1996 (Box 20)
    - Division Street District (Box 20)
    - Historic Districts (Box 20)
    - Broadway Historic District (Box 20)
    - Downtown Historic District
      - General (Box 20)
      - Building Research (Box 20)
    - Washtenaw-Hill Historic District (Box 20)
    - Proclamations 1979, 1985 (Box 21)
    - 303-305 East Ann Street (Box 21)
    - Frank Lloyd Wright, Ann Arbor and Michigan (Box 21)
    - Cobblestone Association and Newsletter (Box 21)
    - Cobblestone Farm, 2 folders (Box 21)
    - Miscellaneous Ann Arbor (Box 21)
    - Jackson and Huron Street Heritage Corridor (Box 21)
    - State Street Improvements and Brochures (Box 21)
    - Ann Arbor Railroad Station (Box 21)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 4 folders (Box 21)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 3 folders (Box 22)
    - Scrapbook (Box 22)
    - Architectural Drawings, 2 folders (Box 22)
    - Kempf House (Box 22)
    - Historic Buildings (Box 22)
    - 312 South Division (Box 22)
    - 1127 East Ann (Box 22)
    - Wystan Stevens, 4 folders (Box 22)
    - Louis Doll, 2 folders (Box 23)
    - Robert Cierzniewski (Box 23)
    - Old West Side Homes Tour, 2 folders (Box 23)
    - News Paper Clippings Ann Arbor News (Box 23)
    - Historic Buildings Research Notes (Box 23)
    - Historic District Commission 1976-1980 (Box 23)
    - Homeless Shelters, Ann Arbor 1983-1988 (Box 23)
    - Ann Arbor Historic Architecture Survey 1973 (Box 23)
    - Michigan Historic Preservation Network Conference 1996 (Box 23)
    - Historical Society of Michigan, 2 folders (Box 23)
    - Allmendinger Organ Research, 3 folders (Box 23)
    - Moses and Jane Gunn House, 712 East Ann St., 3 folders (Box 23)
    - Italianate cube, 311 East Ann St., 3 folders (Box 23)
    - James M. Ashley (Box 23)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 23)
    - Bidlack, Russell, 2 folders (Box 24)
    - Bund, Sally (Box 24)
    - Chapin Family (Box 24)
    - Dr. Chase (Box 24)
    - Cheever, Noah (Box 24)
    - Cheever, Noah (information about, compiled by J. Knott) (Box 24)
    - Copeland, Royal Samuel (Box 24)
    - Corselius, Cornelia (Box 24)
    - Cowherd, Doug (Box 24)
    - Crandell, Alger (Box 24)
    - Culver, Mary (Box 24)
    - Detter, Ray (Box 24)
    - Duff, Lola (Box 24)
    - Fuller, George (Box 24)
    - Groomes, Katherine S. (Box 24)